(upbeat music)
- Hello, English, learners,
welcome back to English.
Hot, my name is Marco.
- And my name is Catherine, and
today we've got a great show for you.
We're talking all about music.
- It's a great topic, I think
everyone loves music,
and well, there's so much
type of music out there,
so that's what we're gonna
be talking about today.
- Exactly, so there's a little bit for
everyone here, even if you hate rock music,
there might be something in
it that you're gonna be a fan of.
- Right, so before we get
started on the dialogue,
we have a couple of words
that we want in preview,
so let's take a look at them
now in vocabulary preview.
- Very cabaret-y preview.
- All right, so this word
sounds a little bit funny.
It looks like it should be
pronounced, differently, we say genre.
- genre.
- Or genre. - It kinda sounds French.
- Is it French?
- I think it comes from French.
It's a GE word, so genre,
it's a soft, soft sound.
- And what's a genre?
- Well, a genre is like a category, so you
could say genre of book or genre of music.
- Oh, movies also have genres, right?
- Yeah, they do, it's like
horror movies, is it genre?
- Okay, or action or suspense, et cetera.
So we're gonna be looking at
music genres on this occasion.
- And some of these genre names actually
have abbreviations, they're long words
that we say in short forms, and this
kind of abbreviation is called an acronym.
All right, so that's another word
that we're looking at acronym.
So an acronym is a short
version of a long word.
- Yeah, usually it's just letters, like USA
is a very good acronym, it
means United States of America.
- All right, cool.
So there are some
acronyms as well in music,
so that's what we're
gonna be looking at,
and many other things, I
guess like DNA is an acronym.
- Yeah, DNA is an
acronym, UN is an acronym.
- All right, great, so we're gonna be
looking at different genres of music.
So let's listen to our
dialogue for the first time.
We're gonna listen to a game show where
people have to name the song and the genre.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome back, music lovers, too.
I love that song, the game show,
where we test your musical knowledge
to the extreme, let's get started.
Team A, guess this tune.
(upbeat music)
♪ I'm carrying your love that you need ♪
- Uh, uh, carrying your love
with me by George Strait.
The genre is country music.
You're right, 100 points to Team A.
Now for our next cut.
♪ All night long ♪
♪ Let me see that song ♪
- Song song by Cisco.
I believe the genre is R&B.
- 100 big points for Team B.
For all of our viewers, the acronym
R&B stands for rhythm and blues.
On that note, DJ, play our next song.
♪ It's just the radio ♪
- Superstar by the carpenters.
- And the genre?
- Hum, um, adult contemporary.
- That's right, 100 points.
(applause)
Uh-oh, that sound means
it's double or nothing.
The songs are more difficult
and the points are doubled.
Let's hear our next song.
♪ Let's see what's going on ♪
- Too easy, that song is Kingslayer by
the Finnish Power Metal Group Nightwish.
You are correct, very impressive, Team A.
And it seems we have a tie.
It's time now for the tie-breaker round.
Each team will be played three songs and
they must tell us the genre of each song
in less than five seconds, Team A.
Are you ready?
Ready?
Let's hear it.
(upbeat music)
Hip hop, classical and gothic metal.
You're right, Team B, the pressure is on.
If you get all of them right, we
will move on to sudden death.
If you miss one, you lose.
D.J., let's hear it.
(upbeat music)
Wrap, disco and, and...
- Fun show Marco, I kind of think I'd be
good at this kind of game, I might win big.
- Well, there were a lot of different types
of genres in there and
a lot of different music.
I don't know, maybe not very popular.
Like, for example, country music.
I don't know if many people outside of
the United States actually know about this.
- Well, there might be different kinds of
country music, but you know, in America,
one of the most famous country
music musicians is Garth Brooks.
And even if I didn't like his music,
I grew up hearing it everywhere.
- But you don't like it.
- You know, it's one of
those things that I like
some kinds of country
music, but it's a huge genre.
That means there's lots of different
kinds of music within country.
- All right.
Well, let's take a look at more of these
genres and now in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, so we talked
about country music.
Now, this is mostly in
the United States, right?
And the South especially
because there's a long tradition
of country music in the
Southern United States.
- So it's very characteristic to have
guitars and a little bit of twang, maybe.
- Twang, what is twang?
- It's a way of saying a word.
So I could say, I'm from Texas,
or I could say, I'm from Texas.
- That's twang.
So kind of like an
accent, a Southern accent.
- Yeah, so Garth Brooks has a famous twang.
- I got friends and loaf, you know,
that's a very famous song of his.
- Twangy.
- Very Southern.
- Yeah.
- All right, so we have country music
and then we saw another genre which is R&B.
- Mm, okay, this is a
little bit more up my alley.
That means this is more
of an interest of mine.
- Yeah.
- And R&B is an acronym
for rhythm and blues.
- All right, so the R&B that we know now
would be some examples of those artists.
- Well, a really famous
artist is John Legend,
has been touring the
world, but his new album.
And that kind of music is R&B.
So we're talking about a kind of music
that mixes jazz traditions with rhythm.
So that means drums and bass.
- Okay.
- Down, down, down, down.
That's rhythm.
- So you have rhythm and
blues, so like the name says R&B.
Very popular nowadays.
Oh, and then we moved
on to something heavier,
something more like
rock style, which is metal.
- Metal, okay, I'm not really
sure why they call it metal,
but metal is a very, very
popular kind of music.
- So it divides into
different categories, right?
In this song, we saw
that it was power metal.
- Yeah.
- But you also have like heavy metal.
- Well, because metal
is such a broad category,
it's a big category.
It's hard to say what certain groups are
unless you're really a fan and you follow,
but there are many different
kinds of metal out there.
And so if you're interested, I
would check it out on Wikipedia.
- Yeah, or let us know if you
know of what's the difference
between power metal and
gothic metal and electronic
metal, so there are so
many different types now.
But moving on to our next genre,
we also saw something that everyone
probably knows nowadays and that's hip hop.
- Yeah, hip hop is a great, great, and
very interesting kind of music grew out of
a lot of people who are
listening to jazz in the
late '80s, especially in
New York, I think Brooklyn.
And it's kind of interesting in the sense
that you take these
old records, these old
vinyls, and you slow
everything down, right?
So you change the speed.
So normal song goes from down,
down, down, down, down, down,
down, down, down, down,
down, down, down, down, down.
- And then you had like some bass in there.
- Yeah, exactly.
- And some lyrics and you have
yourself something like hip hop.
So a very famous hip hop artist
nowadays would be 50 cent?
- Yeah.
- Or for example, also Nelly, right?
Another famous hip hop artist.
- Yeah.
So we have hip hop,
and it's kind of similar,
I don't know, very
similar to rap almost.
- Yeah, but it's different
in that the way the process
for making this kind of
music is quite different.
Yeah, rap tends to be very lyric heavy,
whereas hip hop is very beat heavy, I think.
- Right.
So interesting.
Now we've seen a lot
of these different genres,
but of course there's so
many more that we can't
really look at all of them
in one single podcast.
- That's what our websites for.
You can put your favorite music genres up
on our website and practice your English.
- Exactly.
So, well, why don't we listen to
this dialogue for the second time?
Let's slow it down just a little bit,
and then we'll come back
and look at some more phrases.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome back, music lovers, too.
I love that song, the game show,
where we test your musical
knowledge to the extreme.
Let's get started.
Team A, guess this tune.
- Ah, Karen, you're loved
with me by George Straight.
The genre is country music.
- You're right, 100 points to Team A.
Now for our next cut.
- Song song by Cisco.
I believe the genre is R&B.
- 100 big points for Team B.
For all of our viewers, the acronym R&B
stands for Rhythm and Blues on that note.
DJ, play our next song.
- Superstar by the carpenters.
- And the genre?
- Hum.
- Adult contemporary?
- That's right, 100 points.
- Uh oh, that sound means
it's double or nothing.
The songs are more difficult,
and the points are doubled.
Let's hear our next song.
- Too easy, that song is Kingslayer by
the Finnish Power Metal Group Nightwish.
You are correct, very impressive,
Team A, and it seems we have a tie.
It's time now for the tie-breaker round.
Each team will be played three songs, and
they must tell us the genre of each song
in less than five seconds, Team A.
Are you ready?
- Ready.
- Let's hear it.
Hip hop, classical, and gothic metal.
- You're right, Team B, the pressure is on.
If you get all of them right, we
will move on to sudden death.
If you miss one.
You lose.
DJ, let's hear it.
- Wrap, disco, and... And...
So, it is in a true English pod lesson,
if we don't give you a couple of phrases
and words to make you sound more fluent,
so that's the purpose of
this next portion of our show.
Fluency Builder.
- Okay, so the phrases
that we're gonna look at now
on Fluency Builder are the
ones that we saw in the dialogue,
but we can use, of course, outside
of music or outside of a game show,
and there was an interesting one that he
mentioned when he said, "double or nothing.
" - Hmm, double or nothing.
- It's double or nothing.
Well, this is an interesting phrase, because
I think comes from gambling and betting.
- Right.
- Yeah, so it's a way for us to say,
well, you could double your money,
but if you have a bad answer, if you lose
this round, you don't get anything, yeah.
- So, I guess, yeah, you
do see a lot of people say,
maybe they're betting,
or they're playing a game,
that person loses and says,
"Okay, let's go double or nothing.
" So, give me one more shot to win back my money, or...
- Right.
So, if I say, "Okay,
Marco, you need to tell me
"the capital of
Brazil, you have $50.
" If you get the answer
right, you get $100,
but if you get the answer
wrong, you get zero.
- Right, that's double or nothing.
All right, interesting phrase.
What else do we have?
- We've got a great one
here called tiebreaker.
- So, a tiebreaker.
- Yeah, a tiebreaker, it's a thing.
And sometimes in games,
some people have the same score.
They have the same amount of points.
- So, they're tied.
- They're tied, a tie means
you have the same number.
And if you want to win, you need one winner,
you have to have a tiebreaker to decide.
- So, it could be a
question, or like we saw here,
a tiebreaker round.
- Yeah.
- So, to decide on a winner.
- And this is all-in-a-thing, because
if you get the answer right, you win.
If you don't, you lose.
It doesn't matter if you were tied before.
- Right, all right, a tiebreaker.
And we have one more phrase,
and this one is really interesting.
- The pressure is on, so
if I say the pressure is on,
it almost sounds painful.
- Yeah, it does.
Well, does it mean that I am
being pressured, or what is this?
- Well, so, it's a good question.
The important thing to
look at here is the word on,
because pressure has this
kind of companion word
to put pressure on something,
or to put pressure on someone.
And so, it's the way we say it in English,
and it means that you're going to really
take things seriously from this point on.
- Okay.
- Right, so for example, the
Chicago Bulls were at the peak,
the height of their fame, and
they were just a wonderful team.
And often times, you'd
hear the announcers
say, there's five
seconds left on the clock.
The pressure is on Michael
Jordan to win the game.
- All right, so the opportunity for the
team to win all dependent on Michael Jordan.
- Right, so the pressure,
all of this stuff is on him,
his shoulders, so he has to
score the point to win the game.
- Okay, this is a very interesting phrase.
Why don't we take a look
at some other examples
of how we could use
the pressure is on?
- Example one.
- Carl is really stressed out lately.
The pressure of the entire project
is on him since his promotion.
- Example two.
The pressure is on the president to
guide his country out of the recession.
- Example three.
The pressure is on our entire team.
To successfully come up with a new product
for the Asian market within a month.
- All right, great examples, great phrases.
I think it's a pretty clear now, right?
- It is.
And to make sure that we
understood the whole dialogue,
I think we should take another
listen to it at a normal speed.
And when we come
back, we're talking a little
bit more about one of
my favorite topics, music.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome back, music lovers, too.
I love that song, the game
show, where we test your
musical knowledge to the
extreme, let's get started.
Team A, guess this tune.
♪ I'm carrying your love with me ♪
♪ I'm carrying your love
with me by George Drake ♪
- The genre is country music.
- You're right, 100 points to Team A.
Now for our next cut.
♪ Oh, night long ♪
♪ Let me see that song ♪
- Song song by Cisco.
I believe the genre is R&B.
- 100 big points for Team B.
For all of our viewers, the acronym
R&B stands for Rhythm and Blues.
On that note, DJ, play our next song.
♪ It's just the radio ♪
- Super star by the carpenters.
- And the genre?
- Hum.
Adult contemporary?
- That's right, 100 points.
(audience applauds)
Uh oh, that sound means
it's double or nothing.
The songs are more difficult
and the points are doubled.
Let's hear our next song.
♪ You'll see the night long ♪
- Too easy, that song is Kingslayer by
the Finnish Power Metal Group Nightwish.
You are correct, very impressive, Team A.
And it seems we have a tie.
It's time now for the tie-breaker round.
Each team will be played three songs and
they must tell us the genre of each song
in less than five seconds, Team A.
Are you ready?
Ready.
Let's hear it.
(upbeat music)
- Hip hop, classical and gothic metal.
- You're right, Team B, the pressure is on.
If you get all of them right, we
will move on to sudden death.
If you miss one, you lose.
DJ, let's hear it.
(upbeat music)
- Wrap, disco, and, and,
- All right, so we have
music, different music
genres, which one
are you most lead into?
- As a hard question, I
have very different interests.
I like classical music.
I also like jazz, but I also like rock,
and I also like R&B, so it
really depends on your mood.
- Absolutely.
- Now, they say that music does
really influence people's moods.
- They did a study, some
doctors in America did a study
to see if heart patients,
people who have heart
problems could be
positively affected by music.
And the results said
that, yes, it can be helpful.
- Oh, really?
So maybe it helps them relax, or?
- Yeah, so if you're
listening to the radio,
and you're a song that
you like comes on the radio,
you hear the song, your
heart pumps more oxygen
to your brain, so it
actually makes you happier.
- Wow, what about when they play music
for unborn babies, like
they'll put little headphones
on a mother's belly, and
they'll play like classical music,
'cause supposedly it'll
make the baby smarter.
- Like baby Mozart or something?
- Yeah, exactly.
What do you think about that?
- I don't know.
- I think talking to kids
and giving them books
on that little probably
helps a little bit
more, but I'm not a
doctor, so that I can't say.
- Well, many people do argue now that
they don't make music like they used to.
I guess they say that music that was
made before, the lyrics were more profound.
They were real musicians,
they were composers,
and they wrote lyrics, but
now you just get a lot of
temporary music that doesn't
really transcend into the future.
What do you think?
- I totally disagree.
I think the last 10 years have
seen a really amazing growth
in the music industry, because
more people are communicating.
The internet allows us
to hear all sorts of things
from all over the world, and
so we have great musicians
who can listen to music from Mali,
and they can listen to music from India,
and they have all these
different influences
that we're not there before.
- And so I think it's the
opposite, I think a lot of new
pathways in music have opened up
because of the technology evolution.
- Wow, interesting.
Well, what do you guys think?
Listeners, come to
our website, englishpot.
com, leave your questions and
comments and tell us what you think.
Do you think maybe music
has become better in the
last decade, or do you
think maybe it's not so good?
Well, you do have bad artists, right?
- You always have bad artists.
- Yeah, it's the bad ones
they fade into history.
You never hear from them again, so.
- So, come and let us know,
and also, if you have any
questions or doubts, you can
leave them on the site as well.
- Yeah, we're happy
to answer any questions
you've got, so let us
know what you're thinking.
- All right, we'll see you guys there,
and until next time, bye everyone.
(upbeat music)